University and Student Organizations and Societies - Record Group 39 WLU.RG.0039
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
University and Student Organizations and Societies - Record Group 39
Date Not Yet Determined
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
WLU.RG.0039
x Linear Feet
Online Access
View materials from this collection online via W&L's Digital Archive
Scope and Contents
This record group contains materials created by the University's student and faculty organizations, including fraternities, sororities, and honorary societies, such as official publications by these groups and records about their management.
Fraternal organizations; Greek letter societies; College Students; Washington and Lee University
- General documentation
  - Student Organizations Directory, 1992-2001; 9 Item
  - Student Clubs and Organizations Directory Website
    Scope and Contents
    The University Library has captured the Washington and Lee University's Student Clubs and Organizations Directory webpage using Archive-It. You can view the capturesonline
- Sororities
  - Chi Omega, Xi Lambda Chapter
    - Initiation Banquet program, 1989-04-29; 2 Item
- Fraternities
  - Phi Kappa Psi Records, Washington and Lee University. Phi Kapp Psi
    - Pamphlet with sketches of Phi Kappa Psi Brothers from Washington and Lee who served in the American Civil War, 2005-09; Monroe, Craig T.
      This pamphlet contains information on the 30 Virginia Betas who fought in the American Civil War. It was compiled by Craig T. Monroe, W&L Class of 1987.
      Fraternal organizations
  - Sigma Phi Epsilon Records, 1906-1986; 10 Box
    - Control Folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alumni Board Meetings, no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Alumni Incoming Correspondence, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alumni Newsletters, no date (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brotherhood Development Workbook, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Educating For Brotherhood, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Guide to Brotherhood Development, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Balance Sheets and Bookkeeping Correspondence, no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Billings From National Headquarters, no date (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Billings from Washington and Lee, no date (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Budgets and Audits, no date (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chapter Investment Fund, no date (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Checking Account Summaries, no date (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Fund Raising, no date (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - IRS Tax Information, no date (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Receipt Book, 1978-03-1978-12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Receipt Book, 1980-10-1981-08 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Receipt Book, 1981-01-1982-05 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Receipt Book, 1982-05-1983-03 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Receipt Book, 1984-01-1985-03 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Statements, Reports, Debt Analysis, 2015-05-19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - W&L Fraternity Accounting and Reporting Manual, no date (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Important Charter Members, no date (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Membership Lists, no date (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Membership Status, Initiation Forms, Summaries, no date (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Sigma Phi Epsilon - National Fraternity, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Decals, no date (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Fold Up Map of Charter Sites, no date (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Folders (empty) (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Fraternity Pin (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - National Fraternity Finances, no date (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - National Headquarters - Incoming Correspondence, no date (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Pledge Forms and Information, no date (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - SPE Journals, V. 60, no date (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - SPE Journals, V. 79, nos.1-4, no date (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - SPE Journals, V. 83,no. 2, no date (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Public Relations Guide, 1966, no date (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Regional Meetings, no date (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Ritual 1983, no date (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Study Skills, no date (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Rush, no date (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Rush Books, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Rush Books, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Rush Books, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Virginia Epsilon Chapter, 1906-1966 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Anniversary Celebration, 1976-03-30 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Athletics - Va. Epsilon, no date (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Band Contracts and Social Life Agreements, no date (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Buchanan Outstanding Chapter Award, no date (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Co-eds at W&L, no date (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Duties of the House Officers, no date (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Fancy Dress, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Food Service Information, no date (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Handout for 1984: Mock Democratic Convention, no date (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - House Constitution and Rules (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - House Inspection and Repair Notices, no date (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Housing Guide, no date (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Interfraternity Council, no date (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1960-03-1962-12 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1963-02-1964-12 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1965-01-1967-04 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Minutes of Meetings, (1970,1985,1986) (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Officer's Calendar, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Operational Goals, no date (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Room and Food Service Contracts, no date (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Rules and Regulations of the Va. Board of Health, no date (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Sig Ep Sings, no date (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Unidentified snapshots, no date (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Account Ledgers, 1974-1979 (Box 6)
    - Alumni Relations Information Cards, no date (Box 7)
    - Membership Records, 1906-1918, 1918-1927 (Box 8)
    - Account Ledger, 1981-11-1984-07 (Box 8)
    - Membership Records, 1960-1965, 1965-1973, 1973-1980 (Box 9)
    - Officer's Notebook and an Empty Notebook, no date (Box 10)
  - Delta Upsilon Fraternity Records
    - Directory of undergraduates and alumni of the Washington and Lee University Chapter of Delta Upsilon Fraternity, 1953-05-13; Washington and Lee University. Delta Upsilon
  - Delta Tau Delta. "The Phi Cracker", 1913-1914; Washington and Lee University. Delta Tau Delta. Chapter Phi; 1 Item
  - Interfraternity Council
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1973-01; 1 Item
  - Kappa Alpha Order Model Initiation Ceremony, 2005-08-06
  - Tucker Inn of Phi Delta Phi Initiation Banquet, Robert E. Lee Hotel., 1937-05-04
  - Sigma Pi Sigma
    - Welcome to Washington and Lee's Sigma Pi Sigma chapter website, 2016
      Washington and Lee University's Sigma Pi Sigma chapter created a website to tell about their organization. The University Library captures this site using Archive-It.
      Online Access
      View captures online at Washington and Lee University'sArchive-It webpage
  - Phi Gamma Delta, 1915-04-23,24-1959; 2 Item
    General
    Banquet program, 1915. Booklet, Songs of the FIJIS, September 1959.
    Washington and Lee University. Phi Gamma Delta
  - Zeta Beta Tau scrapbooks, 1948-1949; 1950-1951; 1951-1952; 1956-1957; 1959-1960; 1961-1962; 1976-1977
    A collection of oversize scrapbooks from Washington and Lee University's Zeta Beta Tau (Z.B.T.) fraternity documenting student life, various annual university and fraternity specific events such as Homecoming Weekend, Fancy Dress, home football games, concerts, Mock Convention, fraternity social events, membership, and pledgeship. Scrapbooks include original photographs, artwork, clippings, and ephemera. There are nine scrapbooks between the years 1948 adn 1977.
    College Students -- Social life and customs; Greek letter societies; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Washington and Lee University. Zeta Beta Tau; Zeta Beta Tau (Fraternity)
- Student Publications
  - The Columns, 1943-1946
    The Columns was published by the students of Washington and Lee University from 1943-1946 while publication of the Ring-tum Phi was suspended during World War II.
  - Protest, 1961-1965
  - Muse, 2006-
    Muse is a journal of creative works by Washington and Lee University students.
    The University Library has captured Muse's social media website using Archive-It. You can view captures online.
  - The Periwig, 1928-02; Anderson, Sherwood; Sugrue, Thomas J.; Washington and Lee University. Hybiscus Club; 3 Item
    The Periwig from February 1928 contains works by Sherwood Anderson, Ericson Olif, Ben Lowe, and R. B. Ellard. It was edited by Thomas Sugrue and published by the Hybiscus Club.
    Literature -- Periodicals
  - Probes, 1961-1962
  - Ink, Winter 1970; 2 Item
    Ink was published once a year through the cooperation of Ariel (Washington and Lee University), The Brambler (Sweet Briar College), and Cargoes (Hollins College). Printed at the Journalism Laboratory Press.
  - She Says, 2000-2005
    She says was a publication of the Women's Forum.
  - Gnosis, 2009
    Liberal arts magazine emphasizing scholarly discourse published by Washington and Lee University students
  - InGeneral, 2009-
  - The Spectator, 1989-
  - The Star: Washington and Lee Hillel Newsletter, 2009-2013
  - The Shine, 1932
  - The Mink, Vol. 1 (1920/21)-Vol. 8 (1927/1928)
  - Notes From Underground, 1960s
  - University Touchstone, 1906-06
  - The Thymes, 1975; 4 Item
  - The Voice, 1947-02-11-1947-05-26
  - Ariel, 1962-2006; 21 Volumes
  - Washington and Lee University Political Review, 1982-2007; 7 Volumes
  - Washington and Lee University Journal of Science, 1985-2008; Washington and Lee University. Washington and Lee Biology Forum; 8 Item
  - The Trident, 1993-2008; Washington and Lee University. Campus Reporting Committee, Inc.
  - Ring-tum Phi, 1897-1942/43, 1946/47-
    The Ring-tum Phi is the student newspaper of Washington and Lee University. Its publication was suspended from 1943-1946 during World War II. The university published The Columns in its place.
    Existence and Location of Originals
    The current year of the paper can be found in the newspaper section on Leyburn Library's Main Floor. Many issues can also be found on microfilm, which is located on Leyburn Library's Main Floor.
    The University Library has captured the Ring-Tum Phi's website using Archive-It. You can view the captures online.
  - The Campus, 1942
    A weekly newsletter published at Washington and Lee. Volume 1,#1-10. June-August 1942.
  - The Campus Bulletin, 1943-07-30-1943-08-6; 2 Item
  - The Stone, 2015, 2017
    : The Stone is an interdisciplinary academic journal containing work from the current students of Washington and Lee. The journal's presence and content provoke and answer the question, "What is the purpose of a liberal arts education?" Each issue revolves around exceptional student work from various disciplines-neuroscience, history, geology, journalism, religion, art, music, economics, etc. The work should inform the way people perceive themselves and the world around them, and should encourage a reader to think differently and more broadly about a discipline or subject. We welcome undergraduate creativity and forms of writing/learning beyond the standard essay, including stories, photo essays, and blog posts.
    The University Library has captured The Stone's website using Archive-It. You can view captures online.
    The 2017 issue is a gift of Scott Dittman, Retired W&L Registrar.
  - Pluma, 2016-2020
    Pluma was started in 2013 by students and professors in the Department of Romance Languages who were looking for an outlet for creative expression in Spanish, akin to the work done by Muse in the English-language arena. As the first literary publication for Spanish speakers at Washington and Lee and in the Rockbridge area, Pluma supports creative expression in Spanish and discussion about the cultures of the Spanish-speaking world. This project arose from a desire to establish a forum in which we can share our creative works of prose, poetry, music, and the plastic arts. With the support of the Department of Romance Languages, students actively participate in the process of writing, analyzing, selecting, and publishing the works for the magazine. Through this collective effort, we aim to enhance our use of the Spanish language and foment cultural awareness on campus and beyond.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    The University Library has captured Pluma's website using Archive-It. You can view captures online
  - Common Ground. A Christian Publication on the Washington and Lee Campus., 1991-03-1994-10; 9 Item
    Washington and Lee University. Christians
  - The Footbridge, 1992-03-27-1992-05-27; 2 Item
    Washington and Lee University
  - gnosis, 2008-01-2008-05; Washington and Lee University; 2 Item
  - The House Mtn. Shadow, 1997-2005; Washington and Lee University. Outing Club; 15 Item
    - The W&L Outing Club, 2005-2016
      Washington and Lee University. Outing Club
  - The Nabors Service League, 2000-2006; Washington and Lee University; 12 Item
    - In Memoriam Jonathan Owen Nabors, 1979-1999, 1999-01-18
      Nabors, Jonathan Owen
  - The Seedling, 1999-12-05-2000-02; 2 Item
    Washington and Lee University. Christians; Virginia Military Institute. Christians
  - The Star, 1991-2011; Washington and Lee University. Hillel House; 14 Item
  - take one! and take two!, 2006-2008; Washington and Lee University, Department of Journalism and Mass Communications; 2 Item
  - The Traveller and Traveller, 1991-04-1994-05; Washington and Lee University; 7 Item
  - TUSK, The W&L Republicans, 1977-05; Washington and Lee University; 1 Item
  - W&L Greek Life News, 2008; Washington and Lee University; 1 Item
  - Women's Forum, 1992-1994; Washington and Lee University; 6 Item
  - YAWP, Special Edition: E.C. Big 3 Elections, 1992-02; Washington and Lee University; 1 Item
  - Ampersand Magazine of Arts and Letters, 2018-2019
- Honor Societies
  - Omicron Delta Kappa Records
    - Washington and Lee University Alumni Weekend 2010: Keynote Address by Sidney M. B. Coulling III '46 Videorecording, 2010-04; Coulling, Sidney Mathias Baxter, III; Humphreys, A. H.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Hank Humphreys, 2010.
      Conditions Governing Access
      Digital files of this videorecording are available for use in the Special Collections Reading Room.
      Video recording; Speeches, addresses, etc., American; Washington and Lee University. Omicron Delta Kappa; Humphreys, A. H.
  - Phi Beta Kappa Records
    - Convocation Programs, 2004-2016
      Separated Materials
      Subsequent years are available via the University's Digital Archive at href=https://repository.wlu.edu/handle/11021/26334
      - Fall Convocation, 2012-2022
    - Membership Roster 1911-1916, 2 Item
    - Phi Beta Kappa 1911-1936, Undated; 1 Item
      Booklet includes a history of Washington and Lee's Phi Beta Kappa, Constitution and By-laws, and lists of officers from various years.
    - Annual Banquet, 1955-1971; 3 Item
    - Remarks by Sydney M. B. Coulling at the 60th initiation ceremony, 1971-03-27; Coulling, Sidney Mathias Baxter, III; 4 Item
  - Mu Beta Psi Records
    - W&L Showbill publication, 1969-03-1969-05; 3 Item
    - Initiation and Banquet programs, 1965-04-11; 2 Item
  - Alpha Phi Omega, WLU Chapter Records, 1987-2015
    A copy of Washington and Lee's Alpha Phi Omega (A.P.O.)charter and two commemorative plaques for A.P.O. sponsored fund raisers for the the American Cancer Society - "The Rockbridge Cancer Runs."
    The charter has been removed to the Oversize Drawer for WLU Record Groups
    Washington and Lee University. Alph Phi Omega; Alpha Phi Omega; American Cancer Society
  - Phi Eta Sigma National Honor Society, 2015-05-01
- Other Student Organizations
  - Washington Literary Society, Washington and Lee University. Washington Literary Society
    Includes secretary's books with minutes of meetings, treasurer's books, library books (with records of books lent), roll books, and copies of the Society's constitution. Contains accounts of student debates on current political and social questions.
    Biographical / Historical
    Student literary and debating society with associated library at Washington College, later Washington and Lee University, founded 1814. Popularity declined after World War I, and the society ceased to exist c. 1953
    Washington Literary Society|bgift|cdate unknown
    Related Materials
    Library materials analyzed in Susan M. Coblentz, 'The Graham Philanthropic Society and the Washington Literary Society at Washington College: A Study of their libraries through 1864' (Unpublished M.S.L.S. thesis, Univ. of North Carolina, 1976)
    - Addresses given before the Literary Societies
      - Education and Literature in Virginia, 1850-06-18; Thompson, John Reuben; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - The Progress of the Age, 1851-06-17; Junkin, George, 1798 - 1868; 4 Item (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - An Address Delivered...at Washington College, 1841-06-23; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - An Address Delivered...at Washington College, 1842-06-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - An Address Delivered...Before the Graham Philanthropic and Washington Literary Societies, 1843-09-28; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Eloquence and Liberty, 1846-06-24; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - An Address on the Importance and Advantage of Classical Study, 1849-06; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Self-Development the Object of Life, 1852-07-02; 4 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - The Address Delivered by Gen. Wade Hampton of S.C., 1868-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Address Delivered Before the Literary Societies of Washington College, 1870-06-23; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Address Before the Literary Societies, 1871-06-22; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - The Present Crisis and Its Issues, 1872-06-27; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Address Before the Literary Societies of Washington and Lee University, 1877; Breckinridge, William Campbell Preston; 2 Item (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Address Before the Literary Societies of Washington and Lee University, 1879; Johnston, William Preston; 3 Item (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - The Lesson of Our Civil War, 1886; 3 Item (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Graham Lee and Washington Societies...Final Celebration, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Address Before the Societies..., 1888 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        This address is Vol. 20, no.7 of the Southern Collegian, june 1888..
      - Annual Celebration of the Washington Literary Society, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - The Uses of the Literary Society, 1892; Joynes, Edward S.; 3 Item (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - An Address... Before the Literary Societies of Washington and Lee University, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Some American Needs: An Address, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - An American Citizen, 1916; 2 Item (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Programs and invitations for celebrations and balls, 1873-1890 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Graham Lee Society Anniversary Celebration, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Gift of Col. Walter L. Lewis, USAF
      - Graham Lee and Washington Societies... Final Celebration, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Graham Lee and Washington Literary Societies... Final Celebration, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Records, 1814-1953; 46 Volumes (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Includes secretary's books with minutes of meetings, treasurer's books, library books (with records of books lent), roll books, and copies of the Society's constitution. Contains accounts of student debates on current political and social questions
    - Southern Collegian, 1868-1917/1918, 1927/1928-1942/1943, 1946/1947-1967/1968, 1988, 1996-1998
      A special issue published Oct. 15, 1870 reports on the death of General Robert E. Lee. The publication suspended from 1918-1927, 1969-1987, and 1989-1995.
  - Custis Lee Engineering Society Records
    - Custis Lee Engineering Society Treasurer's Book, 1929; .2 Linear Feet
      Washington and Lee University -- Students
  - Harry Lee Boat Club Records, 1906-1907; Washington and Lee University; 2 Linear Feet
    Boating club at Washington and Lee University, prominent from Robert E. Lee's time to the early 20th century.
    Includes correspondence from W. H. Davy and Sons to George M. Minefree (Washington and Lee University Class of 1908 and president of the Harry Lee Boat Club at Washington and Lee University), and from the E. J. Kerns Company, concerning boats ordered by the club. Also contains correspondence from the C&O Railroad to William Riser (Washington and Lee University Class of 1908) concerning transportation of the boats. A key to the boathouse is included in the collection.
    Boats and boating; Washington and Lee University
  - FOCUS
    - Excelsior: the FOCUS journal of campus thought, Winter 1982
  - University Democrats
    - Kick, 1973
      Kick was a publication by the University Democrats
  - Habitat for Humanity
    - Washington and Lee Chapter Newsletter, Spring 2008
  - SABU
    - SABU informational brochure, Undated; 1 Item
  - G&L: Washington and Lee University's Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual Organization
    - Broadside letter to W&L community, Undated; 1 Item
      In this broadside, G&L releases a statement on the Trident agreeing to publish the group's advertisement but then reversing that decision.
  - Student Association for International Learning
    - Informational sheet, 2000; 1 Item
  - Sazeracs
    Choral music
    - The Sazeracs, 1956
      One vinyl 33 1/3 long play recording by the Sazeracs.Thirteen tracks.Manufactured by RCA.
    - The Sazeracs, audiorecording, 1957
      One 33 1/3 vinyl long play recording by the Sazeracs.Twelve tracks.Manufactured by RCA.
    - The Sazeracs, audiorecording, 1960s?
      Audiorecording containing 24 tracks performed by the Sazeracs.
    - The Sazeracs, Reproduce !, 1965
      One vinyl 33 1/3 long play record.Fifteen tracks recorded by the Sazeracs.Manufactured by Century Custom Recording Service.
  - Fancy Dress, 1914-; 2 Box
    This sub-series contains programs, booklets, invitations, historical information, photographs, and miscellaneous items beginning in 1914, which relate to the annual Fancy Dress Ball.
  - Glee Club
    - Glee Club, 1949; 2 Item
      Three vinyl 33 1/3 long play records.Seven tracks performed by the W&L Glee Club, H.Caleb Cushing directing. Two copies. Copy one autographed by Walter J. Williams,Glee Club president. Produced by Cornell Custom Records.
    - Glee Club, 1953
      33 1/3 LP Record. Published by Recorded Publications Company.
    - Glee Club, The Sixties, Volume One, 1962; 1 Item
      One vinyl long play 33/13 record. Eleven tracks recorded by the W&L Glee Club, Robert Stewart ditecting. Recorded Publications Company.
    - Glee Club, The Sixties, Volume Two, 1962; 3 Item
      One vinyl 33/13 record. Six tracks pPerformed by the W&L Glee Club,Robert Stewart directing. Three copies.
  - W&L Republicans
    - Tusk, 1975-1977
      Monthly publication by the W&L Republicans.
    - W&L Republicans Newsletter, 1977?
    - Washington and Lee Republican Fourm, 1974-05; 2 Volumes
  - SPEAK
    - SPEAK website, 2015
      SPEAK created a facebook page containing information on their events and stories related to sexual assault awareness. The University Library captures this website using Archive-It.
      View captures online via Washington and Lee University's Archive-It page
  - German Club
    - German Club website
      German Club created a Facebook page that contains information about their events. The University Library captures this website using Archive-It.
- Faculty Organizations
  - Washington and Lee Chapter of the American Association of University College Professors (AAUP), 1935-1952